so we were discussing
uh again uh we're in a book which
describes one by one the steps that you
take to reach Enlightenment in order to
become someone who can change this
entire world and help everybody in this
world escape from suffering right escape
from Death itself and uh that suffering
and that uh death is not a necessary
Condition it's a mistake it's just a
small boo boo you know and people on
other worlds have figured it out and
people on this world mostly have not
figured it out so we're just a little
bit behind everybody else in the
universe right uh people still die here
there's still hunger and War here and uh
this book if we practice it well if we
learn it and then go one by one through
the steps meditate on them in a retreat
then uh we could reach a place where we
could be someone who could help this
entire
world escape from all the pain that that
is
here to do that we have to understand
emptiness so we we decided we our
approach has been to go to emptiness
first which is at the end of the book
and then we will go back to the other
steps uh to becoming enlightened but
then each of the other steps will be
informed uh by an understanding of
emptiness which is necessary all right
so we've gone to the hardest part first
and then we'll go back to the beginning
so uh He was discussing on Tuesday uh P
was
discussing uh what kind of conditions do
you need to ga together talk right uh
what conditions do you need to gather
together to see emptiness what kind of
good conditions uh would help you see
emptiness and then he listed some uh I'm
going to
start a little
bit we have to collect certain
conditions probably a few lines up uh
that's close yeah uh
[Music]
first we need a a living
teacher it's not enough to read things
on the Internet or or even read
translations we need a living teacher
who has had some experience of emptiness
and who also has
some uh familiarity with the scriptures
that teach it who can uh God us
everything goes faster if you can find
someone uh who can guide
you like learning piano it'd be like
trying to learn piano from the Internet
or something like we had people at D
Mountain there's a man named will he
decided he's he's going to build his
cabin by himself and he works during the
day then at night he goes home and he
Googles uh the next step in the
construction process
and uh he no YouTube he watches YouTube
like how to install a shower and how to
so he built his shower he did his
Plumbing to his Cesspool then he built
his shower and he poured liquid cement
down the
drain uh then he had to tear all the
drain out and all the St P out again
then he uh fixed all the pipes
throughout the house for the water and
then he looked up a YouTube about
uh sheetrock how to do the sheetrock
over the plumbing he sealed all the
walls in and then the inspector came to
the plumbing and said you have the wrong
pipes for the plumbing so he had to tear
out the sheet
Rod not just tear it out he had to cut
it in strips across the building and
Chang the pipes you know and he's under
time pressure he's trying to finish he
also doesn't have any more money so it's
like that you can't YouTube the step
light
uh you need it would be much better to
have somebody there and say don't will
you know don't pour the cement down the
drain CU okay like that same thing
uher uh do do great things for
Extraordinary People you know like find
special
people uh help
them do errands for them uh D J means uh
remove the obstacles in your heart
examine you know examine the problems in
your life examine the things that are
not going so well and then use the
standard fixes for them which normally
involves not doing the same thing
anymore if someone is irritating to you
someone you
know doesn't listen to you nobody
listens to you
then you have to examine your own life
to see who you're not listening to and
then uh change it it changes right it
doesn't it's not a question of getting
angry at the person or being reasonable
and trying to talk them out of not
listening to you uh you do need you
just uh listen more yourself and then
people listen to you and that's that's
how you fix the problems
right
you ask your dear sweet perfect heart
mama to who is indivisible from a Divine
Angel he
says indivisible from a Divine you ask
them for help okay either you can do it
directly and then we were saying that
you could do it in your mind all day you
can talk to them in your mind and you
could say you know we're studying
emptiness you need a lot of good karma
to study that you need a lot of guidance
you need Divine assistance
and I'm asking you
directly uh in my words and in my heart
to guide me for the rest of my life
especially with regard to these deep
things which are hard for me to see okay
so you ask we
[Music]
ask you gather together these conditions
which will uh what do you call that
be good for the understanding to come
but what's a conditions which are like
conducive
or which yeah which help you to
cultivate they're like fertilizer or
sunlight or water they help you
cultivate that view
right if you don't have those conditions
I mentioned you will never understand
emptiness if you don't have a good human
being living experienced teacher you
won't get it uh if you don't make good
karma with heavy karmic
objects you know go out to stores all
day and buy things for you
know stuff like that di Chong uh if you
don't clean away your own problems how
do you know you have a problem how do
you know you have a b
heart something unpleasant happens
okay how do you know what to do about it
just match it yeah if someone around you
is complaining then stop complaining if
someone around you is irritating stop
being irritating if someone around you
is lying stop
lying like
that and then ask your beautiful heart
Lama perfect heart Lama to help you and
uh if you have those conditions you can
understand emptiness and if you don't
you won't he says they don't
[Music]
in Ancient India there were many systems
of explaining emptiness right there's a
joke in India uh and in Tibet it's
called
lar every Guru has their own teaching
you like that and then there there came
to be thousands of ideas of of our
emptiness right uh especially there came
to be four great ways for four Great
Schools four great Traditions from
ancient India of explaining emptiness
[Music]
right and there were many uh
disagreements among the four classical
schools uh there were many versions of
Tinus taught by Lord gura
himself and they are
contradictory and they were given to
different audiences of different
capacities uh he didn't say the same
thing to the British
Airways Union management that he said to
the diamond mountain people who had been
studying already for 20 years he there
was differences in in the presentation
and they were even contradictory and but
they're all helpful and then you move up
through those viewpoints and then you
get to the highest
one the but the main view that we will
be using this is the highest view in the
open teachings and it is the ultimate
view for all secret teachings so it's
shared by all the highest teachings it's
called umang um means Middle Way
teachings of the middleway
anybody have B
Aspen ex Tylenol
sup yeah IU Prof okay so uh we'll uh I I
want to describe to you uma uma means uh
middle way right
middle and and I I'll just do a quick
demonstration with Aspen with some Aspen
right uh
so what what is this
thing yeah it's an aspirin all
right I'm okay I'm from another planet
okay I'm from Planet B you live on
planet a you know and we are studying
you guys we've been studying you guys
and uh this team where you you start
looking very bad and pale and your your
forehead goes like this and then you uh
you struggle to you've SE have trouble
opening these things
uh and then you get it open and then uh
your hands are shaking and you take
something out and you you take this
thing called to's call
isir aspirin right
uh why why what are what are what are
these things what are these things just
yeah it's a medicine okay I'm from
another planet okay I'm just asking what
are these things medicine what's a
medicine how do you define a
medicine pain it takes away some problem
that you have with some pain some
illness that you have it it takes it
away you but you have to take it right
you you swallow the medicine and then it
takes away some pain in your body
right what does this particular medicine
do yeah I mean this this one normally
most people use it for a headache right
I use it for headache uh use it for
other things but he
right so when you take an aspirin and
your headache goes away then the
medicine worked we say it worked right
right yeah it work does it always
work so let me get this straight on your
planet when you're in extreme pain right
bad pain and you're like hands are
shaking and you try to get the child
thing open and then
uh you you take the pill you swallow it
and then you wait right you why do you
wait yeah it kicks in after a while or
or it doesn't kick in okay right let me
just let me get that straight you take a
medicine whose def definition is that it
takes away your problem and then you
have to wait to see what if it's going
to work work
right
so when it doesn't work is it a
medicine may I remind you that you have
defined a medicine as something which
takes away a problem or an illness
right when it doesn't work is it still a
messine I don't think you can say so I
mean at that time it's not a medicine
right when you take the aspirin and it
doesn't work are there different
chemicals in the aspirin than the
aspirin that did
work this is getting really bizarre I
mean you have to understand how strange
this sounds to our people okay you just
have to appreciate how s strange it
sounds to our people let me get this
straight you take this thing because you
you it will take away a headache but
then sometimes it does and then
sometimes it doesn't right and when it
does it has a certain what in it it's
like a what do you call most of it is
placeo right then there's a little bit
of what do they call it active
ingredient yeah drug facts active
ingredient in each
orange
capet I mean there wasn't anything in
the bottle but that's okay any anything
else
it's
ibuprofen is the active ingredient okay
so there's a few grains of uh IBU proen
that's the active ingredient right so
let me understand I'm just trying I'm
not trying to you know criticize you I'm
just
curious uh you take this thing when you
have a headache and then uh sometimes it
works and sometimes it doesn't but when
it works and when it does word it has
the same active ingredient yes am I
right I mean normally I mean the FDA is
pretty good there are some countries
where they put rap poison in it to save
money uh but this is not one of them yet
um so is the active ingredient
active some sometimes this is like what
do it call there's an expression for
that it's stranger and stranger but
there's some literary expression for
that this is
CH yeah this is curious and curious uh
so you you take this thing and it has an
act what does active
mean it works good
so that's the one that does something
act act it acts right let me get this
straight you take the you take this pill
you swallow it and sometimes the active
ingredient is active and sometimes it's
not I guess you'd have to say that
right and the active ingredient is
equally in every pill yes
right so do you honestly believe that
what takes away your headache is in the
pill that there we come to the Crux of
the question people from my Planet are
curious they want to know they want a
statement from you can choose any repres
of your planet you want anybody sitting
up in the front here it's okay we we
have a what do you call
it a delegation to your planet Rob is
going to represent your Earth okay sorry
you got Stu this uh so let me give this
t uh you do you do your people honestly
believe that what takes away your
headache is inside the pill
yeah and and you also also believe that
sometimes you take the pill and your
headache doesn't go away but you believe
that whatever it is that was inside it
when it did take away your headache was
still inside it when it didn't take away
your headache and yet you still believe
that there's something in the field that
giv your headache this is curiouser and
curiouser
okay what would we say I mean what would
Planet B people say when they say don't
take
aspirin they don't say don't take
aspirin all right your your karmic seeds
need an instrument to express themselves
all right uh you will get to a point
where you don't need to take them and
your headache will go in but but for
most of us the karmas are not strong
enough and they need an agent they need
an instrument through which to express
themselves so that's important to admit
do do we Planet B people still take
aspin say when we get a
headache anyway yeah we do take
Aspen but we do something else first
which
is yeah we want it to work so we need
the cause that makes the active
ingredient active all right there's a
cause underneath the active ingredient
there's something that activates the
active ingredient if that's not there
that it doesn't take away your headache
if it is there it does take away your
headache what we say on Planet B is if
you're a person prone to headaches you
would want to uh
uh be observant and be concerned about
other people's headaches take an
interest in the people around you who
have headaches you know watch out
especially be especially sensitive in
your life to anyone who claims they have
some kind of body pain or some kind of
headache pain like search out those
people you know find those people in
your immediate life who get headaches
who tend to get headaches and then serve
them help them maybe you give them aspir
right maybe you give them uh aspirin
pills or you just trying to help you
give massage their head or give them
some ice packs or like that okay when
you offer them something that will take
that you hope will take away their
headache right you plant the seed in
your mind to see the active ingredient
be active the seed in your mind
created by helping other people have a
similar problem is what activates the
active ingredient when you take an
aspirin and it works it's really because
you have helped someone else in the past
who had headaches or something similar
and when you take a aspin and it doesn't
work it's because the thing that
activates the active ingredient isn't
there which means you didn't take an
interest in other people by the way
taking an interest is like 90% of it
right
has will the aspin that you give them
work you don't know okay don't freak out
but it doesn't make it wrong to offer
them help give them help massage their
head make them a nice pack uh give them
some aspirin whether it works or not is
is not up to you it's up to their seeds
you have to try your responsibility is
to try that plants a seed in your mind
that activates the activ ingredient in
in in your aspin all right so we come to
the big question which was all triggered
by a question about um middle way okay
does Aspen
work be careful does Aspen
work okay next
question this is old you know this is an
old joke I do it was especially a
sensitive at Airways okay I said uh if
you went down the jetway to an airplane
and the stewardess was standing there
with a
clipboard and you know you started it's
always kind of scary moment for me to
step onto the planes like you have one
foot on the jetway and you have another
foot through the metal door and you're
just hoping the jetway doesn't fall down
or something or the plane doesn't fall
down and and you're like I'm on you know
so your foot's about to go on the
airplane
and then the stus says wait wait wait
wait wait wait wait you know and you're
like you get nervous right whenever they
say wait or
something you're you you you're tense
when you feel them get tense you know
and you say what's wrong and they say uh
could you just sign this paper before
you get on the plane you know and and
you say well what paper no one ever
asked me to sign a paper before I got on
a plane before they say just you know
it's just a technicality just sign it
it's okay they're always telling you
that's okay right and then then your
antenna comes up when they say it's okay
and then you
say well what does it say you know can I
look at it and you you grab the
clipboard she's like and you you grab it
and you look at it and and it's an
insurance waiver you know and then you
say
uh why are you asking me to sign an
insurance waiver you know they say well
you know this is a pretty new Airline
and we have some new aircraft here and
uh
we pretty much figure out how to flat
you know like most of the time it goes
really well you know you you're very
likely to get to where you're going
safely you know and just
sometimes you know it falls
down you know and then you know those
nasty Insurance suits and things we just
want to avoid them you know don't
nothing to be concerned about you know
would you get on the pl
if this really happened in an airport
would you get on the plane I mean you'd
turn around and you'd go to some other
Airline right you'd go to the terminal
you know ticket Sellers and you'd say I
want to get on another airline you I
want my money back and I want to get on
another does their play
Work get no stop the sometimes thing
okay stop the sometimes thing you know
I'll tell you something this is from my
heart okay this is from my heart people
on your
planet for the whole history of your
planet you know 50,000 years
of of of civilization you know once you
started to be civilized it's been 50,000
years right you've been doing things for
50,000 years and
you and and everything you do works
sometimes everything you've been doing
works sometimes and you you've gotten
used to accepting that you know you've
gotten accustomed you have become used
to saying believing that it's not so bad
that an aspirin works sometimes right
and you pay for a whole bottle of aspin
knowing that half of them are not going
to work you know they don't give you
half back you don't Rite to you know who
is this equate company and say it didn't
take my headache away could I have the
money back from half the pills that
didn't work you you you laugh you're
laughing you laughed when I said that it
means you you honestly think it's okay
that they charge you for the whole
bottle you're used to it and you accept
it and you shouldn't you should you
should object to things that don't work
you should turn around and go to the
ticket counter and get something else
you see you don't have to live like that
okay you don't have to keep doing things
that work sometimes and don't work
sometimes cuz when they just work
sometimes they don't work don't you get
it it's like the pr you know I don't
want to know if it works sometimes I'm
going to get on a plane that works all
the time okay but you got used to it and
you are some kind I don't know it's very
pitiful to watch you it's very sad to
watch you you know because it's not just
aspir every single action you undertake
in your whole day is is sometimes worse
and sometimes doesn't work and you're
just playing odds all day you know
you're just playing odds all day I read
a book by one of the greatest stock
analysts of all time right and he said
in the end it's a crapshoot you know he
said nobody knows is it going to go up
or down I was lucky but nobody knows
it's just gambling you know taking an
aspin is gambling you get in your car to
go to work you turn the key you don't
know that you won't die on the way to
work and you accept that you accept that
chance and you actually say your car
gets you to work you know you have the
tarity I almost
said you have the gut to say you get to
work in a car we wouldn't even say that
on our planet if the cars killed the
people one time out of a thousand we'd
say the car isn't word that's not how
you got to work
if a car kills you one time out of a
thousand the car didn't get you to work
something else did right and you you try
to understand okay you guys on your
planet try to understand whatever you
want to work you have to serve somebody
else first you have to show some kind of
kindness to somebody else first then the
thing will work and that's what makes
the thing work and it's not the active
ingredient and it's not the
gasoline and it's not the battery it's
kindness kindness is the active
ingredient helping other people is the
active ingredient and then everything
works all the time okay and and the
things you say work don't work and and
stop putting up with it you know stop
getting on airplanes that might fall
down stop taking asps that don't work
every time cuz that doesn't work that
means they don't work you know and you
think I'm crazy you know you're sitting
there like this guy's weird you know and
uh I don't know
[Music]
anyway
uh consider the possibility that
everything could work all the time you
could make investments and you would
make money you could do yoga and you
would get th and strong you could study
L and you would conquer death just it
would just work you see everything would
work and you wouldn't have to work so
hard it's not working is not the hard
thing not knowing if you're the work is
going to have a result it's the hard
thing you know going to work is not so
hard not knowing if the work is going to
make money or not is that's hard the
uncertainty of your approach you know
sitting on the plane and wondering if
it's going to fall down that's almost
worse than falling down you see to live
a whole life uncertain if what you're
going to do it's going to work why don't
you just stop them why don't you just do
things that work see okay so maik how
did I start off on this Aspen thing you
know how now we're more behind on
homework
six okay middle
way did I say that Aspens never
work I am saying they don't work is it
impossible to make them work no could
they work yes yes
do they always work
no so one extreme is saying they always
work no they work and you believe that
because you take them and then the other
extreme would me would be for me to sit
up here and say under no conditions will
and enough been work if for you to say
that they work and for me to say that
they don't work these are two extremes
the middle way middle way this is it
right you get this you get the rest of
the book The Middle Way says there's a
cause behind the cause and if
you act if you if you find that cause
which is kindness towards others and
serving others then it will always work
okay I didn't say Aspen worked and I
didn't say aspirin didn't work I said
under certain conditions aspirin will
work if you've been kind to another
person so I'm now I'll check let's check
in does aspirin
work say no does aspin not work no does
aspin work under certain conditions what
are those conditions kindness okay
that's all that's middle way okay that's
middle way then the highest Middle Way
school is called
Tang that means pranga or consequence
they believe that the effectiveness of
I've just given you an argument
right they believe that the
effectiveness of an argument itself for
truth doesn't lie in the
argument the effectiveness of an
argument for truth does not even lie in
the argument where does it
lie in your honesty to
others okay if if my presentation
convinces you it's because you've been
honest to others if you don't believe my
presentation it's because you've been
dishonest to others not even my words
work not even the argument to which I
dedicated my life to bring to you right
to this day it doesn't work it only
works if you've been nice cool all right
here we
go there's a very unique teaching of the
middle way school there's a very unique
teaching of the middle way school they
say this thing called tend out which
means dependent origination forget that
big word okay it just means things work
because of kindness just think like that
things work when you've been kind to
people that's dependent or that's the
meaning of dependent Orin okay if you
put a seed in your mind for an aspen to
work by being kind to someone who has a
headache then the Aspen will work that's
dependent origination all
right what's
emptiness emptiness is these don't
work it's even more uh extreme these are
not these are not ASP these are not
medicine these are not medicine and
these are not aspin and they are sure as
hell not pain relievers or headache
relievers because they don't work
[Music]
okay take away all the aspirin in the
world world that don't work because
you've been kind okay take away all the
Asen in the world that I'm
sorry yeah okay take away all the as in
the world that were but not because
you've been kind okay how many askp for
none okay got it that's emptiness you
cannot find an aspen that works that
didn't work because you were kind to
somebody all the other kind of aspin are
just not aspects that's emptiness
right are those two ideas like do they
do they what do you
call do they support each other or not
you know are they antagonistic or are
they uh what's the
opposite yeah are they two sides of the
same coin are they what what's the
opposite of antagonist
[Music]
compatible maybe compatible is good who
said compatible yeah that's good is it
compati is it compatible if I
say there's no aspir in the world that
works if you're not kind okay that's a
negative statement right there's no
Aspen in the world that works if you're
not kind that's EMP is got that hold
that in your mind then over here is when
an aspin works is because you're being
kind to someone else that's a positive
statement that's dependent origination
and this one is emptiness do they
mesh do they mesh absolutely are they
the same no one is a negative statement
there's no aspet in the world that
doesn't work from kindness and one is a
par statement every aspet in the world
that works does so because of kindness
do they mesh or are they
antagonistic they mesh this creates a
space for this to
be you see the fact that there's no
aspin in the world that doesn't come
from kindness creates a space for all
the asps that do come from kindness got
it the emptiness creates a space for the
truth the screen creates a empty space
for the words to
be okay got it sorry
okay so the unique thing about the
highest middleway school is that they
said you want to know what the
pagination is you know I want to know
what the meaning of the pation is it's
empty and you want to know what the EMP
emptinesses is dep
pen they mesh so closely that they are
opposite sides of the same coin you
couldn't take
away I mean modern American coins are
what they're like sliver you know you
could peel it into two but
normally you know it' be like what the
back of the paper depends on the front
of the paper right you can't peel off
the front of the paper and not hurt the
back of the paper there not two pieces
it's one piece of paper you you can't
have emptiness without the pen
origination and you can't have the pen
origination without emptiness because
they are just opposite sides of the same
coin it's only the highest School of
middleway that expresses that
clearly like we got two whole lines done
the compassionate teacher Lord Buddha
okay the compassionate
teacher he he he he came to address
audiences of people and then you know a
good
teacher is uh winging in a lot of the
time they walk in they have a lesson
plan and then they look around the room
and they say that's not going to work
for these people and they just change
they just go down or they go up to they
either go down to a lower version or
they go up to a higher version they
don't stick to what they plan because
you know half the people are falling
asleep or half the people are like ah
and then they they say oh I got to crank
this stop these people are better than I
thought you know so Lord Buddha CH means
he would observe his audience and he
would see that their minds were higher
than he expected or lower than he
expected and then he would adjust just
his
presentation so in a case where he was
addressing sort of uh I did it once it
was the New Age Festival in Sun
Valley okay he had
to he had to like can we say dumb down
his argument
okay in order to get those
people to stop being so attached
to aspirin is an aspirin an aspir that's
do you want to know what Atma means or
do self self Buddhist say there's no
self I mean let's put it in plain
English is an aspen
ASP is an asp let's say it this way is
an aspen Med be careful be careful right
okay got it Aspen is not of medicine why
it doesn't take away your
pain it's worse than that
it sometimes takes away or or seems to
take away your pain got
it isn't Aspen an
aspen
no isn't Aspen and Aspen if You' been
kind to someone who gets heavy yeah yeah
get used to that all
right what if I'm lying you know what if
everything I said is dumb what if
everything I said is
wrong I mean what's the worst that can
happen you run around giving ASP to
people okay I mean you'll be a nice
person and everybody will like you
that's the worst that can happen Okay
and uh if I'm telling the truth then
you'll never not have your headache go
away right all right
here we
go so for people who are at sort of a
basic level they couldn't get a higher
presentation Lord Buddha told them he
didn't talk to them about the as okay he
didn't say an as is not an as he didn't
say uh
[Music]
what is that that's the heart Sutra in
the heart Sutra Lord Budd as is not as
tyl is not not you know no he did he
did nothing nothing is anything you know
but he can't say that to the Sun Valley
New
Age fesal all right so he has to say you
know people ask him a question what's
emptiness I was in Brazil with Ken you
know and some guy I was translating and
he was in real diser and some guy said R
what is the cosmic Vortex of the
universal spirit in the soul of the
absolute you know and R's looking at him
you know and then he says what did he
say you know and I tried to translate
and he said
he anyway
uh those people cannot get the thing
that ASP is not Aspen you don't go there
because they won't come back and that's
the worst thing you can do same with the
yoga class you don't teach Advanced
things in a beginner's yoga class cuz
the worst thing that can happen will
happen what they'll never come back
they'll give up yoga you know so the
worst thing you can do is overwhelm
people right you you got to back up and
say
look do you have control over your body
is your body
you no why
not cuz you can't tell it what to do do
you have control of do you run your body
no I don't raise your left
ey okay I'll ask you to do you run your
body how can you say you don't run your
body you just lifted your left
up yeah I mean ultimately you don't run
your body you can't control your body it
will do things and you can't it will get
a Cancer and you will talk to it and say
don't have a c and it won't listen to
you there's an illusion of control right
when you're
young and then no one of the frustrating
things about aging and I've been around
some aging people recently some 80y olds
you know and their their hearts are
breaking because they don't have they're
realizing they don't have control and
they never did have control and it's
very very painful to to know that you
don't have control after all after 75
years of believing that you have control
then to find out you don't have control
that's very sad better to tell those
people when they are 30 or 40 look you
don't really have control over your your
body you know then they won't be so hurt
later you know and you don't really have
control over your mind right
you will get into depressions or
sadnesses and you can't control it in
the present moment in the present moment
you can't control these things so relax
a little bit you know learn in your 30s
and 40s to relax when you get to 70 or
80 and it becomes obvious you'll be a
better person you'll be a more patient
person and a nicer
person is that enough just to be a nicer
person as your body falls apart we say
no we say no we say find out the causes
why the body falls apart and stop it
before it falls apart and don't try to
be a nice person while it falls apart
you know don't try to be a person who
copes with problems well be a person who
makes them non
events learn to make them not happen in
the first place these lower
viewpoints and almost every book you
ever read about Buddhism mus in the
Barnes and Nobles uh they are lower
viewpoints they they they're helpful
they are what do you call comforting and
they're
useless okay
yeah we don't have any contr body and
mind how is it possible for
us yeah good good good if I don't have
control over my body and mind in the
present moment when you say present
moment gim Michel you're implying what
that I have some kind of control over my
body and mind in the future like I have
control over the body and mind I'm going
to have in six months but not right now
okay I like to call it the current body
and mind is hard cement and the future
body and mind is wet cement right uh but
if the current body and mind Teddy
saying are heart cement how can they
think to affect the future body and
mind okay how how do you get your mind
to want to affect the wet cement if it's
already hard
cement Grace of your
teacher which comes from good C
[Music]
okay then Lord Buddha met people who
were a little bit more capable he found
audiences who were more uh trained and
he
said then he told people you know some
stuff
works because of something inside it and
some stuff doesn't work because of
something inside it he fudged it okay
for some better audiences he fudged it
said some stuff some aspin is aspin and
some aspin aren't aspin he fudged it
just so they wouldn't freak out he
didn't go to Planet a and tell them
nothing in your whole life worked that
you ever tried in your whole life you
know because people would lose hope he
said you're ain't doing a good job most
of what you do is good um there's a few
adjustments to be made right he he he
fudged it got it yeah but if things are
coming from us how come Lord Buddha some
sometimes find people are more sometime
that's a good question he said Lord
Buddha how could Lord Buddha if if
things are coming from yourself and if
Lord Buddha is a perfect being how come
he ran into people who could get it and
other people who couldn't get it that
would imply that Lord Buddha didn't get
it if we meet an irritating person what
does it imply that we've been irrita
we've been
irrita right oh all
right that's one way to answer the
question that's one way to answer the
question
uh okay the other way is to is to say
that they perceive themselves as not
getting it but Lord Buddha sees them as
10 L of Bas because nobody else is
allowed in his
Parise but those same bisas don't see
themselves as Poli and they are not but
they are okay they not to
he said then there were other ones that
he said look things are not exactly
real uh but they do have some quality in
them of their own okay fire is hot but
it's not 100% real it's not what you
thought it is but it does have a quality
of being hot things do have something in
them but not in the way you thought he
fudged it he did Advanced fudging right
all right next
young even the higher
ones to the very highest disciples he
said nothing has inside of it anything
that
works nothing has inside of it anything
that works not a car not an airplane not
an aspir not a
book nothing nothing works nothing has
anything inside of it it works if you
understand what this thing says it's not
because it's in the book it's because
you have helped other people understand
things okay there's nothing in this book
which can help you if you perceive
something in the book which can help you
it's because you've been kind to other
people
congratulations all right
okay we'll stop and take a break shortly
okay the ultimate intention of Lord
Buddha and the ultimate idea or belief
of Lord Buddha is only expressed in the
final position that we mentioned nothing
has anything in it that works only that
position is the is the real truth the
rest was fudging it
for lower audiences right
[Music]
he's going to change gears here okay
he's going to change gears here you'll
be able to finish your sixth
homework he's going to tell
us you see Buddha can see
everything in all time that's what a
Buddha is right they can see all events
in the past they can see all events in
the future they can all they can see all
events now we are locked into like a
tiny little box called the present
moment you see we are [__]
uh we we are like in a we live in a
closet we live in a closet our whole
lives like there's a I saw these big
rambling homes today I was on Central
Avenue and cach Avenue I love Arizona
wealthy people's homes they just spread
out they just go down the block you know
and I just imagine people like if they
if they forgot the corn chips in the
kitchen they got to walk like half a
mile to get to the kitchen again and
then come back you know like they don't
build up because it makes it too hot
right so they just take over lots and
they build room they add rooms on that's
what this building is it was a small
house and they kept adding rooms on so
uh why did I say
that yeah so it's like you live in one
Closet in a huge Arizona rambling
wealthy person's house you know and you
spent your whole life in the closet we
live in a in the present moment it's
it's not your normal condition all right
you made some kind of mistake it's not
the nature of your mind your mind's
nature is that you're supposed to ramble
throughout the whole house of all time
in all space your mind has the power
already in it its natural condition is
to see all things in all
times I can't be getting a can't be
getting a text message
[Music]
your mind's own nature is to see all
things in all times you are now in a
temporary you know it's like you're it's
like you have a fever or something it's
a temporary illness that you have and
and it won't be like that you know okay
so Lord Buddha 2 and a half th000 years
ago set in
motion events that he knew would lead to
this night
because he saw this night 2 and half
thousand years ago he also sees Saturday
and Sunday he knows and I don't know
whether I'll be able to prepare the
homeworks but he knows okay like he's
his mind is not limited so he
saw he saw certain people in history who
would be who would carry his message who
had carry this word this idea about
emptiness is very very difficult and
there are only a few people throughout
history who have carried it on Purely
and it has been lost in centuries and it
has come back in other centuries and it
has been it's so difficult and so rare
and so precious that there are times
when it was lost and there are times
when it has come back uh and then he's
going to
describe how that happened all right
after your
refreshment okay let's start again uh
we'll just do like a half
hour uh and and and from what we are
about to do you will be able to do
through the sixth homework okay so um
you should finish the sixth homework by
tomorrow evening all
right you do need uh this is a
the Lord Buddha uh made a
prediction uh in a place called beta you
uh there will be a glorious monk uh very
famed and his name will be the the the
okay his name will be
the jpa he will
destroy the Viewpoint that things
exist or that they and that they don't
exist right he will destroy he
will destroy the idea that Aspen either
exists or doesn't exist but you already
know the difference right you're all
right with that if you nod you might get
to go home okay you already know the
difference right does it
exist no does it not exist no no does it
exist under certain
circumstances which are kindness all
right so you're already caught up to
AR
okay he avoided the two extremes of
saying that aspirin works or saying that
aspirin doesn't work he threaded his way
between those two extremes
right he was a matchless comment Ator on
what Lord Buddha meant okay
so somebody who has seen emptiness
explains emptiness in a generation or
maybe in
every 15
Generations okay and then uh they teach
people and then they they leave or
something and then those people try to
explain it to other people and and what
happened between Lord Buddha
and I am AA who came 700 years later was
that there was a big gap there there
wasn't anyone who taught it uh
completely correctly all
right from the point of view from of
someone who had seen it directly so
emptiness taught by someone who has seen
it
directly is completely different from
emptiness taught by someone who hasn't
seen it and and there wasn't anyone who
had seen it so so there was
a the teachings on emptiness what do you
call it
declined uh for five over 500 years then
uh thear came and
uh he's amazing like just totally
totally totally amazing and you can't
imagine but to
read Nar in the original is to hear
somebody say aspirin exists aspirin
doesn't EX say you know aspin with
kindness exist aspin without kindness
doesn't exist that's why it doesn't
exist and he just keeps going like that
line after line
like
Exquisite and seemingly you know
contradictory and very very brief and
very beautiful you see and he just got
up and said aspin works and aspirin
doesn't work and he went on like that
it's like the heart Sutra
it seems like the deeper someone sees it
or if someone's really seen it then they
just say little things his his text is
little and the lines are little it's
called the roote text on
wisdom he just it's tiny little part
it's like the heart CRA it's tiny it's
short and it has all this weird stuff in
it like Aspen works doesn't work and and
that's the way Aya talk that's the way a
talk okay they they're trying to say
things don't work or like that okay so
then he passed
away uh and it was a long time before
another Arya showed up uh who taught
that particular subject in that way and
that was CH okay let's see if he gets
there uh
we must seek to understand emptiness as
it was understood by narina in 200 ad
all right what we have at our disposal
is aran's teachings on emptiness if you
want to understand emptiness study Aran
okay that's all the Buddhist is often
too difficult so there's a weird uh
thing that goes on in Buddhism okay
normally the longer a philosophy stays
in this world the more corrupt it gets
right
normally
uh Someone Like Jesus says something and
then there's hundreds and hundreds of
years of interpretation and normally the
interpretation gets weirder and weirder
as time goes by and probably farther and
farther away from that the original
intent of the
person uh in Buddhism the opposite
happened okay like Lord Buddha was
teaching people whose Minds were much
more meditative than ours so they caught
things faster in 500 BC in India than
they do nothing so then people kept
coming and clarifying for the current
generation so there has been a long and
glorious line of teachers who have
clarified emptiness for the present
generation and and it's gotten sweeter
instead of more corrupt you know it's
gotten more and more simple fly or
clearer in a way so anyway Master CH
came in I don't know 650
ad let's see if he comes
[Music]
uh you can
see many individuals writing books
giving explanations about
emptiness uh which claim to be very
profound any of those presentations
which is in accordance with how n taught
it that is what the Buddha meant
buty but if someone tries to teach you
emptiness which is essentially different
than the way we just talked about the
Aspen okay if someone tries to teach you
some weird kind of emptiness like black
hole emptiness or don't think about
anything emptiness or everything's an
illusion nothing matters all those kind
kind of
emptinesses it is quite certain that
they are not telling you what the Buddha
meant okay that's not what Lord Buddha
meant right if you hear an explanation
of emptiness which is in any what do you
call considerable way or uh substantial
way different from the Aspen thing you
just got it's wrong okay that's all okay
it's not just the case that there
were people in tibc who were LMBO means
uh fools he's being very uh what do you
call harsh he's being harsh he says I'm
not he says I'm not just talking about
the fools here in Tibet he says
tring even in India even in Ancient
India Master he mentions Master Baba Rea
and other Masters these people wrote a
thousand pages each about emptiness they
wrote books that were a thousand pages
long Jona started a sect which has
survived for many centuries in Tibet and
he says they're just simply wrong on the
crucial point
when it comes down to nuts and
B when it comes down to Nar Nar
Jun little statements like Aspen doesn't
work Aspen's not Aspen there's nothing
in the Aspen they don't get
it they just don't get it okay my uh
personal advice is that if someone gives
you a teaching on emptiness which cannot
be immediately applied to your
life and which doesn't require you to be
kind to others as a direct result of
understanding that emptiness then it's
wrong it's it's it's not useful and it's
wrong
okay the sign that your understanding
Emptiness is correct is that you
compelled to be more and more kind to
others if there isn't that bridge or
that connection between emptiness and
kindness it's wrong okay
some
people said I'm trying to follow neous
thinking all right Aspen is not ASP I'm
trying to follow that thinking they go
but they didn't get it okay they didn't
get it and you can read hundreds of
books like that you can read you know
hundreds and hundreds of books the books
that are written about about emptiness
are the most crazy and most worthless
you know they're like if you understood
the physics of how to cause an atomic
reaction or if you understood how to
make a jet airplane engine right and
then there was some aborigin from
Australia who wrote a book about
airplane engines from you know like big
round go to little thing poot come out
you know and then and then you tried to
use that to build an aircraft
engine uh the explanations you see in
99% of the books are the same they are
completely unusable and worthless in
trying to understand emptiness they're
just flatly wrong
okay so people either Tred to fall in
the G up but didn't get it because it's
hard right if someone comes up and says
aspin's not aspirin and they don't know
what they're talking about then then
then then there'd be real confusion
right then people would do all sorts of
weird things they would stare at walls
for their whole life or they would think
nothing mattered or they would do crazy
things they wouldn't go and help
peopleas other people flatly refuse to
follow in thei thinking not only
that even attack the G okay they said
there's this crazy guy he says aspirin
doesn't
exist but we all take aspirin you know
then he then he changed his mind and
said aspin did exist but then he said it
didn't work and later on he said it
always
work you know and it's just crazy you
know
so if you don't follow
and you just make up something okay I
mean that's the worst right it's one
thing to follow an ancient wrong
tradition it's another thing to just
start making up stuff on your own and
and what I what I pains me to see is
when people study pretty well for a few
years and then they take off and they
say I don't need to study anymore they
stop their
studies and and then their view gets
weirder and weirder every year they're
away from the source
they start teaching weirder and weirder
stuff until 5 years later you can't
recognize what they're saying you know
for the first year what they're saying
is sounds like what they learned and
then they just keep what do you call
they want to make it more and more
Sensational every year so then they just
start making up stuff and then 5 years
later I don't recognize them as my
student I don't recognize them as saying
anything I would want them to say I they
just started to what do you call it
improvise
okay uh you can't stop studying you
either have to see something directly or
you have to keep studying you can't
study for a while and then go off and
improvise okay all right
[Music]
you this is a very famous statement
we'll go for about 15 minutes more
okay this is CH all right uh 650 ad this
is what he
said if someone were to what do you call
it go away from uh on a
path diver diverge diverge if someone
were to diverge from the teachings of
the
garer uh and and then lose those lose
that idea lose those ideas okay what
aspirin is not aspirin aspirin is not
not aspirin aspirin will work aspirin
doesn't work aspirin does work uh
aspirin Works under certain conditions
of being kindness to other emptiness can
only be understood in the context of
compassion emptiness can only be
understood in the context of compassion
right someone who leaves that system
someone who who who tries to teach any
other kind of
emptiness they will
never uh reach happiness they will never
reach happiness peace not not possible
to reach
peace uh without
kindness they have lost the teaching of
the two truths okay they have lost the
teaching on the two realities okay what
are the two realities is there an aspen
here is there Asen
[Applause]
here is it what it does it do what it
what you
thought no so we say this is deceptive
it's called deceptive reality is it
real yes it's there is it lying to you
yeah okay until you heard that its power
was granted to it by kindness it was
lying to you all those years you tried
to take
medicine but didn't connect it to your
kindness to others then those Aspens
were lying to you okay they were what we
call deceptive reality right that in
itself is Ultimate
Reality so there's two realities the
fact that they were lying to you
is the
truth got it okay so there's two truths
or there's two realities number
one none of the stuff in your life that
you thought worked worked the way you
thought it did we can even go so far as
to say the name of my next
book nothing works I didn't write it yet
but I know the
title nothing works we can go so far as
to say nothing works everything is lying
to you everything you thought worked
didn't
work every action you ever undertook
that was successful wasn't successful
for the reason you
thought if you ever got anything from
doing anything it was random good
luck okay that's kind of
disturbing and that applies to the other
six billion people also no action being
undertaken in the world today which
which works works all right you all
right yeah by anybody from the morning
to the night thousands of actions
multipli time 6
billion none of them Works none of them
people try to make money people try to
get a boy or a girl you know people try
to become famous people try to fix their
health nothing that they do works it's
it's mindboggling if you don't feel
mindboggling you don't get the extent of
the problem right the problem is mind
botling no action undertaken by any
human being in the last 50,000 years had
anything to do with what they were
hoping to
get your JW supposed to to drop you know
drop your JW no
okay I just want to see if you can
control your jaw all right
uh d g
so those people don't understand those
two
realities it's not possible to ever
reach any degree of Happiness without
understanding what we talked about
today it's not possible it it will never
happen cannot cannot be happy if you
don't understand that things are coming
from how you treat other people it
cannot happen it will never happen
you'll never be happy and you'll never
get the things you hope nothing
okay there's no second door to happiness
there's no second method to happiness
that's all there's one right
uh so you don't really have any choice
you have to find out what what in the
teach what did he think you know you
don't those of you who get
it you did a little what was
a when you when I finish the Aspen
explanation something happened to you I
cursed you I cursed you you will never
be able to take an aspen again and
really believe that it's working right
and then then you'll start doubting your
car and then you'll start doubting
everything you say nothing works I
cursed you you know the next time you
get a headache you're going to be thrown
into doubt you'll probably get another
headache on top of the first headache
okay all
right now you're now you're going to
doubt everything Financial strategies
yoga scriptures telephones
computers aspirins operations
everything you try doesn't
work they they're neutral they could
work and they could not work depending
on if you're kind to other people that's
all all
right and there's no second way to peace
you have to understand that all
[Music]
right now the guardian that lived 18
centuries ago all right he passed away
some people say after 700 years I don't
know okay but
Joo
uh who was the next great person to
understand emptiness and and express it
clearly in this way was Master so
Lord who was it that really grasped
under emptiness after NE okay after
NE Shake
there was a teacher who was predicted by
the Buddha
right there was a teacher who saw
emptiness he was the disciple of N and
his name
was I always confuse the two KES okay
who are the two k there's a d and
there's a CH so don't confuse them D is
the
logician much earlier different school
okay Chand which means the famous Moon
what's that mean famous
Moon how many people in the world see
the moon on a given
day I mean who don't have
clouds everybody okay so his name is
famous as the moon as well known as the
Moon I mean you just go out and look up
and you see the Moon how many people saw
the moon today
everybody I mean unless they had clouds
or they didn't go outside the the Moon
is everywhere and he's as important as
the
moon this Isa speaking right the person
who brought Buddhism to tiet is speaking
the person who brought the L to tiet is
speaking he says uh it's only the
teachings which came down to to Chand
uh which will help you to see
emptiness they will help you to see
emptiness so we can say that
after was the greatest teacher of these
things of EMP
[Music]
after the Buddhism reached toet many
many great Scholars came many many great
wise people came and they understood
emptiness in the way that Chand Master
CH so inet in the early days there was a
a lot of pure understanding of
emptiness
what's but
[Applause]
[Music]
but those teachers were faced with a lot
of Sun Valley New Age
audiences and they had to adjust their
teaching like they ran into Tibetans who
couldn't get it you know as the years
went by the teachers the teaching spread
into
you know and people of different
capacities wanted to learn about
emptiness and then they saw that these
people wouldn't get it if they came up
and said an aspirant's not an aspirant
so they kind of fudged it but then the
fudging became the the party line the
fudging became the party L and things
got messed up okay things got messed up
and a lot of people started really
getting
confused because their teacher's teacher
had had fudged it for the convention the
new age convention and that's what they
heard
okay by the time OFA in the 1400s right
13 late 1300s early
1400s by the time of jets OFA 600 years
before now
things were so bad that that toaa
started to doubt every every every
tradition being taught inet okay it was
so bad that he began to doubt every
version of emptiness
[Music]
into then J decided to go to India and
try to get the straight poop okay from
an Indian he said things in tiet are bad
maybe in India people still understand
EMP so he did he made a plan to go to to
India and he was going to study with uh
somebody named uh
nagab who was alive in his time not nag
okay nagab and somebody name named the D
Mah Mitra okay like DAV Mitra okay
but somebody one of his teachers advised
him to
wait and then that teacher
uh he went to a t d named bajani okay
China he had contact with a Divine being
he said you don't have to go to India I
got connections
all right so you ask me what you need to
know I'll ask vaj
okay and then he
gave uh a record of the questions he had
asked this Divine Angel called
men the Garland of the deathless nectar
of the highest medicine okay that's just
some book
he gave
this
uh but there were problems with the
record okay like I don't know the the
the MP3 got
corrupted right there were problems with
the
text
and so J wasn't satisfied with that
record of questions and answers okay
from
[Music]
so so he made requests in his heart to
his heart Lama who was indivisible from
a Divine angel named MRI all right the
angel of wisdom right he in his heart he
realized that his Sweet Holy root llama
was no different than the Divine angel
of wisdom he knew that he and then he
asked her or him uh help me understand
these things help me to understand these
things
uh one he spent a lot of time trying to
clean away his b Karma and trying to do
200 new projects to make new good or
okay
and he really tried
to in meditation to to meditate on those
deep subjects that he was taught
okay and after many years of trying he
met maushi face to face you know and
there are Beautiful Stories first he had
a translator he had an
intermediary uh named what was his name
m uh he was
a he was a sheep
herder
who who was very very devoted and he had
good meditation and he he was able to he
was just a sheep her but he met uh this
Angel he was able to meet this Angel
directly out on in The
Meadows in the grass he met Mish it's
very beautiful story and then so SOA had
questions about emptiness he was going
to go all the way to India right and
then lamaa said not
necessary ask me and I'll ask MRI and
then he could see M buta couldn't see M
and then he said you know this is kind
of a hassle why don't you just teach me
to see M and he did okay CH
shall there are he says there are many
ways to meet a ttic daddy there are many
ways to meet a Divine Angel okay he
gives a list
number
one you can get sort of a
hallucination because of Prana going in
weird channels in your body okay Prana
can kind of like shoot into weird places
in your channels and you can kind of
think you're seeing an angel all right
and it it's sort of a shaky thing
or in deep meditation you can have a
vision of an angel in with your eyes
closed
okay or you can meet them face to face
really face to face as if you had met
your next door neighbor right J
guess which one TOA did with
M the last one okay they met face to
face not like a a dream or not like a
vision but they met Fai he was fortunate
enough to meet this angel face to face
and and interact with the angel as this
as the angel student
let me see how long this is going to
[Music]
go I better stop there okay
I'm just going to do it really fast
okay I'm sorry I'll keep you another 10
minutes uh
and it would seem that after asking
questions of this Angel jenta was unable
to grasp the answers completely okay
after asking questions after meeting
this Angel directly and after asking his
questions he was unable to understand
all the answers it would seem
that at the end of the first time SOA
means it would seem that what's that
mean
he was pretending not to
understand
so told him look there's a human teacher
in Tibet right now his name is
randawa you you talk to
randawa okay you take my answers to
randawa and ask him to help you and that
was one of toa's great first teachers
later on
so Kaa passed him and began teaching
Rand and then they had these prostration
fights because no one knew who was the
teacher and who was the student all
right but that's another story
[Applause]
uh he this is talking to you won't be
able to clear up all your doubts only
with but take the teachings I have given
you from the
angel if you keep working hard on the
answers I have given you and then you
refer back to the Classics of ancient
India on emptiness
okay you will come to understand
emptiness right you take the questions I
answers I gave you check in with randawa
Master V then go back to the ancient
Classics and then it will come he
predicted he made a prediction you will
understand sh
sign JEA went back to collecting Good
Karma by doing nice things for Holy
beings like you know going out buying
things for them and stuff like that uh
and then uh he collected enough Good
Karma and he cleaned his Bad Karma that
he had a direct vision of a Lama named
Buddha palita okay Buddha palita is a
llama
who he's a teacher who lived in India
between n and Chand okay between a n and
master
Chand he lived just before Master chti
right he wrote a book explaining Aaj
somebody else complained about it Chand
came to his rescue a couple centuries
later all right so Buddha had it right
but he got criticized during his
lifetime later on cherti came along and
cleaned up the problem and and what do
you call it what do you call it when you
prove someone was right in the first
place yeah who said that Vindicated yeah
that's good he Vindicated uh Buddha
palita okay so here soapa had a vision
of Buddha
palita then he had a vision it's a
beautiful Vision it's in that big red
book about he saw Buddha Pita's book
written across the
sky uh and then he came to an
understanding of
the higher mod school okay that we
talked about if you understand the aspin
that's your school already
right he got
it you sure you want all this tonight
another five minutes okay I'm sorry some
of you wanted to go home I'm
sorry
uh then he start
uh he also had visions of other earlier
Indian Masters all right in his
Visions uh but he didn't uh what do he
say he didn't what do you call he he
didn't count them as being like
he underrated them okay in his mind he
he thought oh I love CH and I love budha
but these other guys I don't know about
them they're probably not so important
he was thinking that it's Ona all right
just Ona then uh M send him a
message a Lama
Nam okay TOA
means person who has really good
connections with uh
High
beings and there's beautiful beautiful
beautiful stories about TOA the most
famous one is
what yeah that's how TOA was told by
Mishu to take a partner okay and then he
doubted the instructions and he thought
maybe he was crazy so he asked TOA to
ask M again and then TOA had a dream and
and MRI told soapa to go get a partner
and stop fooling around and go get a
partner right so anyway that's another
story uh to told Jessa that M wanted him
not
to underrate these other Indian
scriptures
right if you are able to study carefully
the great Classics on emptiness written
throughout Indian history you'll be able
to help many other people and it's the
same with you guys okay I could get up
here and not tell you anything from
soapa you know I I can repackage it in
good old plain English for you and
that's what I do for British Airways and
stuff like that you know I don't mention
soapa I don't mention dhak sorry chti I
don't go through all this historical
stuff you know know and I don't quote
anybody I just give them the aspirin
thing but the purpose of this particular
gathering for the
next 10 years is that you get the real
the real thing I'm not going to what do
you call
it water it down all right you got to
hang in there okay we're going to get
the real
Classics and that's what man told okay
stop
water go get to the
class when Jessa finally got it about
the Aspen he freaked out and he got a
huge crush on Lord
Buddha okay it's really weird it's
really weird if you read uh his later
poetry he was writing love PS to Lord
Buddha you know the Buddha is kind of
this old historical guy and we don't
have it's not like
you have a crush it'd be weird to say
you have a crush on the Buddha right but
he did once he understood the aspirin
pain he immediately fell in love with
Lord Buddha really in love like like
couldn't think about anything else all
day long like a real Crush you know like
a permanent crush on somebody all right
which is kind of nice all right you like
run through red lights and stuff like
that so he wrote a book
called what's
that the essence of eloquence chuma
what's CH
Chung the little one Jessa wrote two
books called the essence of eloquence
they're not at all connected okay the
shorter one is a praise of Lord
Buddha because he taught the pen
inertion it's very famous we should
learn it someday it's a nice thing for a
weekend like that what do you call it
Place Masuk it's a nice thing for a
weekend uh he wrote a love poem to Lord
Buddha because he said I'm I have a
crush on you because you Tau to P
origination and it's beautiful it's a
great book about the pen origination
okay
we're almost done okay one more minute
maybe was a very very
famous llama inet called bod okay
bod uh he wrote 130 page 130 volume in
cyclopedia of Buddhism right it's it's
unbelievable okay so Bodo was out doing
Pro he was doing what do you call he was
circum ulating in in hassa somewhere
okay then he heard a beggar reciting
Lord Buddha sorry jessa's Crush poem to
Lord Buddha all right so the beggar
heard the poem and learned it by heart
and then he was just walking around
singing this song to crush po
okay
[Music]
uh
then who was very very great scholar he
thought oh this must be a book by
Nar this poem this love poem must be by
n it's so perfect it must have been
written by n right and then
so then he said no no it must have been
written by CH you know it's got to be
either n or it's too
perfect then he heard quotations from
the G and CH in the poem and he said
wait a minute it can't
be qu he's
quoting then realized it had to be a
third person okay I'm trying to give you
the three big people who have carried on
emptiness on this planet up to the
present day okay there are three people
whose names you have to know cuz if it
wasn't for
them it would be gone it would be gone
from this world nobody would understand
that nobody you know 6 billion people
would be what do you call it
the situation would be hopeless
irretrievable okay only three people
carried it on up to the present time and
and that that was
AR
CH and all right
then uh the beggar said this was written
by toaa somebody named toaa bodong went
to meet
toaa he got irreversible faith in TOA ja
chin he went to try to find
TOA buta had already left this world to
serve others in other
worlds
okay today J he wasn't able to meet him
he lost his
chance he he you know you need gold to
meet a big llama right in the old days
so he had some gold he was going to
offer some gold at
somea and zapa had already passed to
another world so he took the gold dust
and he just drew it in the air and he
said may I meet him in some lifetime
okay
so and then there's a story how that
gold floated to the air and landed in
gandan Monastery wherea had been
living
Etc
uh so that's all then jenta wrote a book
called clarification the illumin of the
true thought of the
Buddha and that's that's where our
lineage comes from all right so those
three
Aras okay those three people who saw
emptiness the garina is is known to be
have seen emptiness directly I'm not
sure about
Chand jeta is said to have seen
emptiness
directly but that that's it that's who
carried in this world so you should know
who they are all right and the only
reason we have it now is because of them
so you should at least you should know a
little bit about them right okay all
right